{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The western coast of India receive very high rainfall in summer mainly due to",
            "optionA": "  Tropical location ",
            "optionB": "  Nearness to sea ",
            "optionC": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  Himalayas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe western coast of India receive very high rainfall in summer mainly due to Western Ghats. Due to the greater width of the mountains, the rain bearing winds have to necessarily travel a longer distance and have more time for the drops to coalesce and precipitate as rainfall, resulting in higher rainfall.",
            "keyString": "94215s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following places, the average annual rainfall is highest at ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Shillong ",
            "optionD": "  Thiruvananthapuram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong the following places, the average annual rainfall is highest at Shillong. The average annual temperature in Shillong is 17.1\u00b0 C. Precipitation here averages 3385 mm. ",
            "keyString": "94399s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A rainy day as defined by the Indian Meteorological department is a day when the rainfall at a point received is",
            "optionA": "  0.5 mm to 1 mm in 24 hours ",
            "optionB": "  1.1 mm to 1.5 mm in 24 hours ",
            "optionC": "  1.6 mm to 2 mm in 24 hours ",
            "optionD": "  Above 2.5 mm in 24 hours ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA rainy day as defined by the Indian Meteorological department is a day when the rainfall at a point received is Above 2.5 mm in 24 hours. As per the IMD guidelines, rainfall amount recorded in a day should be 2.5 mm or more for considering a day as a rainy day. ",
            "keyString": "94560s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the nature of monsoon rain from Guwahati to Chandigarh?",
            "optionA": "  Irregular Nature ",
            "optionB": "  Crescent or Growing Nature ",
            "optionC": "   Diminishing Nature ",
            "optionD": "  Cyclic Nature ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoisture carrying winds when travel from Guwahati to Chandigarh, blow over land and keep loosing their moisture content in the way without picking any new moisture that is why monsoon has a diminishing nature from Guwahati to Chandigarh.",
            "keyString": "94717s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The amount and intensity of monsoon rainfall is determined by the frequency of",
            "optionA": "  Western disturbances ",
            "optionB": "  Dust storms ",
            "optionC": "  Cyclones ",
            "optionD": "  Tropical depressions ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe amount and intensity of monsoon rainfall is determined by the frequency of tropical depressions. A tropical depression forms when a low pressure area is accompanied by thunderstorms that produce a circular wind flow with maximum sustained winds below 39 mph.",
            "keyString": "94871s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The north-western India receives substantial rainfall during winter months because of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  South-west monsoons ",
            "optionB": "  Retreating monsoons ",
            "optionC": "  North-east monsoons ",
            "optionD": "  Westerly disturbances ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe north-western India receives substantial rainfall during winter months because of Westerly disturbances. Western Disturbance is an extra tropical storm, which give rain to North and Northwest India during winter. ",
            "keyString": "163025s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following pairs of places have most marked difference in total rainfall per annum even though located approximately along the same latitude?",
            "optionA": "  Bengaluru and Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai and Visakhapatnam ",
            "optionC": "  Ajmer and Shillong ",
            "optionD": "  Nagpur and Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAjmer and Shillong have most marked difference in total rainfall per annum even though located approximately along the same latitude. There is not much rainfall in Ajmer all year long. The average annual temperature is 24.7\u00b0 C in Ajmer. The average annual rainfall is 557 mm. The average annual temperature in Shillong is 17.1\u00b0 C. Precipitation here averages 3385 mm. ",
            "keyString": "163070s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How do dust storms in summer affect the temperature?",
            "optionA": "  Increase it ",
            "optionB": "  Decrease it ",
            "optionC": "  No effect ",
            "optionD": "  Cannot say ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDust storms occur most frequently over deserts and regions of dry soil, where particles of dirt are loosely bound to the surface. Dust storms in summer decreases the temperature. ",
            "keyString": "163191s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why does Western Ghats and Eastern Ghats both receive sufficient rainfall but Deccan Plateau receives scanty rainfall?",
            "optionA": "  It is a rain shadow area ",
            "optionB": "  It is located parallel to wind direction ",
            "optionC": "   It is away from the coast ",
            "optionD": "  Rain bearing clouds are absent ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWestern Ghats and Eastern Ghats both receive sufficient rainfall but Deccan Plateau receives scanty rainfall because it is a rain shadow area. Deccan plateau falls on the leeward side of western ghats so the rainfall is very scanty in this area. ",
            "keyString": "163350s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The place which experiences minimum and maximum temperature of - 28.3\u00b0C and 15\u00b0C respectively is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Srinagar ",
            "optionB": "  Shimla ",
            "optionC": "  Kullu ",
            "optionD": "  Leh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe place which experiences minimum and maximum temperature of - 28.3\u00b0C and 15\u00b0C respectively is Leh. ",
            "keyString": "163646s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the major cause of 'October Heat'?",
            "optionA": "  Hot and dry weather ",
            "optionB": "  Very low velocity winds ",
            "optionC": "  Low pressure systems over the Indo-Gangetic ",
            "optionD": "  High temperature associated with high\nhumidity ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the month of October as the monsoon retreats, the feeble high pressure builds up over North India symbolizing clear skies, due to which the temperatures rises again and as the whole area has been drenched by recent rainy season the humidity also rises which becomes unbearable for people to sustain the combined effect of both.",
            "keyString": "232051s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "From where does the heat come in the environment?",
            "optionA": "  Insolation ",
            "optionB": "  Radiation ",
            "optionC": "  Condensation ",
            "optionD": "  Convection ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEarth receives its heat from sun in the form of Insolation (short wavelength) and radiates it back in the form of long wavelength waves. Our atmosphere is transparent to short wave radiations but traps long wave radiations that is why it is heated from below.",
            "keyString": "232240s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following states, retreating monsoon has more effect?",
            "optionA": "  Orissa ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Tamil Nadu, retreating monsoon has more effect. When the retreating monsoon blows from the northeast across the Bay of Bengal, it picks up a significant amount of moisture, which is subsequently released after moving back onto the peninsula. ",
            "keyString": "232399s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the South-West Monsoon, Tamil Nadu\nremains dry because",
            "optionA": "  It is located in rain shadow area ",
            "optionB": "  Temperature is so high that wind does not get\ncooled ",
            "optionC": "  Winds do not reach this area ",
            "optionD": "  There is no mountain in this area ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the South-West Monsoon, Tamil Nadu remains dry because it is located in rain shadow area. Tamil Nadu has rain during the monsoon season due to the southwest trade winds which blow towards the northern hemisphere. Tamil Nadu receives rainfall in the winter season due to northeast trade winds. ",
            "keyString": "233400s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who introduced the term 'monsoon'?",
            "optionA": "  The British ",
            "optionB": "  The Mughals ",
            "optionC": "  The Arabs ",
            "optionD": "  The Chinese ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Arabs introduced the term 'monsoon'. The word monsoon is derived from the Arabic word 'mausim', meaning season. It was first used by Arabic navigators to describe the seasonal winds of the Arabian Sea. Although the term monsoon actually means a seasonal wind, it is often used to refer to the torrential rainfall associated with these winds. ",
            "keyString": "236724s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants are associated with the social forestry programmes in India?",
            "optionA": "  Teak ",
            "optionB": "  Neem ",
            "optionC": "  Eucalyptus ",
            "optionD": "  Banyan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEucalyptus plants are associated with the social forestry programmes in India. Eucalyptus is a genus of over seven hundred species of flowering trees, shrubs or mallees in the myrtle family, Myrtaceae commonly known as eucalypts.",
            "keyString": "298131s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following functions performed by a forest help most in controlling drought?",
            "optionA": "  Forests act as water sheds ",
            "optionB": "  Forests bring rainfall in monsoon ",
            "optionC": "  Forests lower the temperature of the environment ",
            "optionD": "  Forests prevent soil erosion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tForests bring rainfall in monsoon help most in controlling drought. It helps in recovering the water loss that can lead to drought. ",
            "keyString": "298313s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India's forest sponge iron plant is at",
            "optionA": "  Kothagudam ",
            "optionB": "  Kurnool ",
            "optionC": "  Cuddappah ",
            "optionD": "  Kavaratti ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia's forest sponge iron plant is at Kothagudam. Established in 1982, the plant was inaugurated by the then President of India Gyani Zail Singh. Said to be the first sponge plant in Asia, till the year 2000 it was running with a huge profit. ",
            "keyString": "298476s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Economically the most important forests of India are",
            "optionA": "  Tidal forest ",
            "optionB": "  Thorn forest ",
            "optionC": "  Evergreen forest ",
            "optionD": "  Tropical deciduous forest ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEconomically the most important forests of India are Tropical deciduous forest. As per the economic resource pooling of India, the tropical Deciduous forests are the best ones in terms of export, import and revenue.",
            "keyString": "298634s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statement and identify with the help of the code the tree with which the statement is related to? The branches of this tree root themselves like new trees over a large area. The roots then give rise to more trunks and branches. Because of this characteristic and its longevity, this tree is considered immortal and is an integral part of the myths and legends of India.",
            "optionA": "  Banyan ",
            "optionB": "  Neem ",
            "optionC": "  Tamarind (lmli) ",
            "optionD": "  Peepal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe branches of banyan tree root themselves like new trees over a large area. The roots then give rise to more trunks and branches. Because of this characteristic and its longevity, this tree is considered immortal and is an integral part of the myths and legends of India. ",
            "keyString": "298788s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following states on the basis of ascending dates of the onset of monsoon :\n1. Uttar Pradesh\n2. Kerala\n3. West Bengal\n4. Rajasthan",
            "optionA": "  2-3-1-4 ",
            "optionB": "  3-2-1-4 ",
            "optionC": "  3-1-2-4 ",
            "optionD": "  1-2-3-4 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following states on the basis of ascending dates of the onset of monsoon West Bengal, Kerala, Uttar Pradesh and Rajasthan. ",
            "keyString": "364480s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is true with regard to the erratic behaviour of Indian monsoons?",
            "optionA": "  Uniform duration but varying amounts of rain from one year to another, as well as at different places ",
            "optionB": "  Uncertain date of onset and withdrawal, as well as unequal distribution of rain ",
            "optionC": "  Uncertain date of onset and withdrawal as well as varying amounts of rainfall during different years ",
            "optionD": "  Uniform duration but varying amounts of rain from place to place ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statement that is true with regard to the erratic behaviour of Indian monsoons is Uncertain date of onset and withdrawal as well as varying amounts of rainfall during different years. ",
            "keyString": "364709s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are nine coastal states in India but half of the sea salt is manufactured in the coast of\nGujarat because",
            "optionA": "  Gandhiji started Salt Satyagrah in Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Less rain and relative humidity is best for the\nevaporation of the sea water ",
            "optionC": "   Salt is exported from Kandla port ",
            "optionD": "  The salinity of water near coast of Gujarat is very high ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Gujarat accounts for over 70% of the production in country. The availability of favourable conditions such as arid climate with low rainfall and low relative humidity contributes largely towards salt production in the region. e.g. Sambhar Lake. ",
            "keyString": "364891s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "National Flood Commission is related to",
            "optionA": "  Flood ",
            "optionB": "  Disaster Management ",
            "optionC": "  Drought and flood ",
            "optionD": "  Poverty Alleviation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational Flood Commission also called as \"Rashtriya Barh Ayog\" was established in 1976 to evolve a coordinative, integral and scientific approach to the problems arising in controlling floods in the country and to strategise a national plan to fix priorities so as to implement them in the future. ",
            "keyString": "365067s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct sequence in the decreasing order of contribution to the forest cover on India ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Dense forest - Open forest - Mangrove forest ",
            "optionB": "  Open forest - Dense forest - Mangrove forest ",
            "optionC": "  Dense forest - Mangrove forest - Open forest ",
            "optionD": "  Open forest - Mangrove forest - Dense forest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct sequence in the decreasing order of contribution to the forest cover on India is Open forest - Dense forest - Mangrove forest. ",
            "keyString": "365231s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following two states are prone to cyclones during retreating Monsoon season?",
            "optionA": "  Kamataka and Kerala ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab and Haryana ",
            "optionC": "  Bihar and Assam ",
            "optionD": "  Andhra Pradesh and Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe withdrawal of monsoon from the northern region and then from the whole nation gradually is termed as monsoon retreat. During the monsoon retreat it rains heavily in Odisha and Andhra Pradesh as cyclonic formation in Baengal are confined to this region. ",
            "keyString": "421970s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following types of vegetation is referred as Monsoon forest?",
            "optionA": "  Tropical Dry-evergreen forests ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical Moist-deciduous forests ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical Semi-evergreen forests ",
            "optionD": "  Tropical Dry-deciduous forests ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTropical Moist-deciduous forests is referred as Monsoon forest. The tropical deciduous forests are also called monsoon forest because the trees in these forests shed their leaves during dry season and re-grow during monsoon. ",
            "keyString": "422012s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The south west monsoon engulfs the entire India by",
            "optionA": "  5th June ",
            "optionB": "  15th June ",
            "optionC": "  1st July ",
            "optionD": "  15th July ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlthough the monsoon commences on Kerala coastby 29 May to 1st June, it takes time to cover entire India. The normal date observed by which it covers entire India is 15th June.",
            "keyString": "422130s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The retreating monsoon withdraws from the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  West coast to the east coast ",
            "optionB": "  North to the south ",
            "optionC": "  North-east India to the west coast ",
            "optionD": "  North-west India to Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe retreating monsoon withdraws from the North-west India to Bengal. ",
            "keyString": "422229s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Monsoon is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Temperature changes ",
            "optionB": "  Seasonal reversal of winds ",
            "optionC": "  Humidity difference ",
            "optionD": "  Pressure differences ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMonsoon is caused by pressure differences. The monsoons usually happen due to the differential heating of land and water. Thus, the changes in pressure conditions also affect the monsoons. Normally, there is high pressure in the tropical eastern-south Pacific Ocean and low pressure in the tropical eastern Indian Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "422320s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Forest Research Institute is at",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionB": "  Cambay ",
            "optionC": "  Dehradun ",
            "optionD": "  Simla ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tForest Research Institute is at Dehradun. Forest Research Institute (Deemed to be) University Dehradun (FRI), made a humble beginning as Forest School established in 1878. ",
            "keyString": "508435s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why have the incidents of flood risen in India recently?",
            "optionA": "  Rise in annual rain ",
            "optionB": "  Deposition of silt in dams ",
            "optionC": "  Deforestation in drainage zone ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe incidents of flood risen in India recently because of Deforestation in drainage zone. Although there are many reasons for increasing floods but deforestation has predominantly caused by surface clearance which in turn leads to surface run off and loose sediments again flow with them towards rivers increasing its sediment load and making it more prone to floods. ",
            "keyString": "508483s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Deforestation results in :\n1. flora destruction\n2. fauna destruction\n3. ecological disbalance",
            "optionA": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionC": "  1 only ",
            "optionD": "  1 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeforestation results in flora destruction, fauna destruction and ecological disbalance. Deforestation is also causing environmental imbalance by affecting the biodiversity adversely. Forests serve as safe habitats for a large species of flora and fauna. Several species of animals and plants are dying each day due to loss of habitat and lack of food. ",
            "keyString": "508617s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following states has the largest forest area to its total land area?",
            "optionA": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionB": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Jammu and Kashmir ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMizoram has the largest forest area to its total land area. Mizoram has 90.38% of forest cover to geographical area and this is the highest in the country. Mizoram has highest percentage of area under forest cover. ",
            "keyString": "508750s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The driest place in India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Leh ",
            "optionB": "  Barmer ",
            "optionC": "  Jaisalmer ",
            "optionD": "  Bikaner ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe driest place in India is Jaisalmer. Jaisalmer is a former medieval trading center and a princely state in the western Indian state of Rajasthan, in the heart of the Thar Desert. ",
            "keyString": "508861s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Operation Flood refers to",
            "optionA": "  Blue revolution ",
            "optionB": "  Green revolution ",
            "optionC": "  White revolution ",
            "optionD": "  All the three ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOperation Flood refers to White revolution. Operation Flood was started by National Dairy Development Board (NDDB) in 1970s. The objective of this programme was to create a nationwide milk grid. The result was that India became the largest producer of Milk and Milk Products. Operation flood is called White Revolution of India. ",
            "keyString": "577526s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following place is the most humid place of India?",
            "optionA": "  Mahabaleshwar ",
            "optionB": "  Cherrapunji ",
            "optionC": "  Udhagamandalam ",
            "optionD": "  Mawsynram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe alignment of hills of Garo,Khasi and Jaintia inMawsynram is in a way that clouds get stuck in these hills and do not move and keep pouring water. The phenomenon is known as funneling effect and due to this Mawsynram in Meghalaya is the wettest place. ",
            "keyString": "577696s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not affect Indian climate?",
            "optionA": "  Monsoon ",
            "optionB": "  Ocean currents ",
            "optionC": "  Proximity to equator ",
            "optionD": "  Existence of Indian Ocean ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs India lies completely in warm water zone of tropical and sub tropical region, oceanic currents matter comparalively less than other given option. ",
            "keyString": "577800s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following forest is grown in waterlogged areas?",
            "optionA": "  Evergreen Forest ",
            "optionB": "  Deciduous Forest ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical thorn Forest ",
            "optionD": "  Mangrove ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMangrove forests grow in waterlogged regions in theintertidal zones of coastal regions. They face tides everyday and water level keeps on fluctuating. Mangrove forestshave strong roots and the belt of these trees protects the coastal areas from disaster such as cyclone. ",
            "keyString": "577892s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sal' is a very important tree of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Tropical dry deciduous forest ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical rain forest ",
            "optionC": "  Thorn forest ",
            "optionD": "  Alpine forest ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSal' is a very important tree of Tropical dry deciduous forest. These \u201cdry\u201d forests occur in regions with heavy rainfall for part of the year followed by a marked dry season. They are dense with greenery during the wet summers, but become a starkly different landscape during the dry winters when most trees shed their leaves. ",
            "keyString": "578067s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Monsoon retreat is marked by:\n1. clear sky\n2. high pressure conditions at the Bay of Bengal\n3. rise in temperature on land",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMonsoon retreat is marked by clear sky. North east monsoon winds bring rainfall over the coastal region of Tamil Nadu while the retreating monsoon is marked by clear skies and rise in temperature. ",
            "keyString": "639572s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why does the west coast of India receive more rainfall from south-west monsoon than the east coast?",
            "optionA": "  Unlike the east coast this coast is straight ",
            "optionB": "  The Western Ghats obstruct the winds\ncausing rainfall ",
            "optionC": "  The east coast is broader than the west coast ",
            "optionD": "  The Eastern Ghats extend parallel to wind\ndirection ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Western Ghats are more elevated and continuous as compared to Eastern Ghats, that is why they (Western Ghats) block the moisture containing winds and receive more rainfall. They also lie opposite to moisture laden monsoon winds. ",
            "keyString": "639623s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The rains along the western coast of India are ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cyclonic ",
            "optionB": "  Convectional ",
            "optionC": "  Orographic ",
            "optionD": "  Monsoonal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rains along the western coast of India are orographic. Orographic or relief rainfall is caused when masses of air are forced up the side of elevated land formations, such as large mountains (often referred to as an upslope effect). The lift of the air up the side of the mountain results in adiabatic cooling, and ultimately condensation and precipitation. ",
            "keyString": "639752s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is heavy rainfall on the western coast of India but very little in the Deccan because",
            "optionA": "  The Deccan plateau is situated in the rain shadow of the Western Ghats ",
            "optionB": "  The region is bypassed by the south-west monsoons ",
            "optionC": "  Lack of high mountains in the Deccan ",
            "optionD": "  Of some unknown reason ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is heavy rainfall on the western coast of India but very little in the Deccan because the Deccan plateau is situated in the rain shadow of the Western Ghats. The Deccan Plateau to the east of the Western Ghats receives significantly less rainfall than the coasts. As the summer (wet) monsoons approach the West Coast of India, they rise up the western Ghats (mountains) and the air cools. This cool air is less able to hold moisture and it is released as rainfall. ",
            "keyString": "639867s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs of cities have the largest annual average rain difference as compared to the other three pairs?",
            "optionA": "  Jabalpur and Nagpur ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai and Pune ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata and Bhubaneshwar ",
            "optionD": "  Guwahati and Shillong ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumbai and Pune have the largest annual average rain difference as compared to the other three pairs. Mumbai/ Bombay receives on balance 2168 mm (85.4 in) of rainfall per year, or 180.7 mm (7.1 in) per month. In Pune, the monsoon lasts from June to October, with moderate rainfall and temperatures ranging from 22 to 28\u00b0 C (72 to 82\u00b0 F).",
            "keyString": "639972s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The western disturbances which cause winter rain in India originate in",
            "optionA": "  Pakistan ",
            "optionB": "  Bay of Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  West Asia ",
            "optionD": "  Himalayas ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe western disturbances which cause winter rain in India originate in West Asia. An approaching western disturbance, however, is expected to cause a change of weather in northern and central India and western parts of Maharashtra. A WD is associated with rainfall, snowfall and fog in northern India. Upon its arrival in Pakistan and northern India, clouds along with rain and snow also arrive.",
            "keyString": "730849s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The place to receive annual rainfall below 50cm is",
            "optionA": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionB": "  Leh in Kashmir ",
            "optionC": "  Coromandal Coast ",
            "optionD": "  Konkan Coast ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLeh region in Kashmir is a cold desert, the rainfall here is very less (<50cm).Meghalaya and Konkan coast receives heavy rainfall in monsoon (>200 cm) and Coromandel coast receives more than 100cm rain due to retreating monsoon.",
            "keyString": "731167s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following states receives the highest rainfall during winter months?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Kerala ",
            "optionC": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionD": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTamil Nadu receives the highest rainfall during winter months. Tamil Nadu lies on the windward side for these winds and hence gets more rainfall during the winter season. The air, over Siberia cools creating a high pressure area north of the Himalayas. ",
            "keyString": "731201s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mumbai receives more rainfall than Pune because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Mumbai is on the windward side ",
            "optionB": "  Pune is at a-greater elevation ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai is a coastal city ",
            "optionD": "  Pune has greater vegetation than Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumbai receives more rainfall than Pune because it is located on the coast and Pune is in the interior. Mumbai lies on the windward side of Western Ghats while Pune is located on the leeward side. Windward refers to the direction from which the rain-bearing south west monsoon winds approach the land from sea. ",
            "keyString": "731823s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The temperature of Thiruvananthapuram is lower than that of Mumbai in May and higher than that of Mumbai in January, because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Thiruvananthapuram has cold current and Mumbai is faced with warm current ",
            "optionB": "  Thiruvananthapuram has higher rainfall in summer and it is nearer to the equator ",
            "optionC": "  Thiruvananthapuram is on the windward side and Mumbai is on the leeward side ",
            "optionD": "  Thiruvananthapuram is Vegetated while Mumbai is not ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe temperature of Thiruvananthapuram is lower than that of Mumbai in May and higher than that of Mumbai in January, because Thiruvananthapuram has higher rainfall in summer and it is nearer to the equator. ",
            "keyString": "731991s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "\"Reserved Forests\" are forests",
            "optionA": "  Reserved for hunting ",
            "optionB": "  Reserved for commercial exploitation and prohibited for grazing ",
            "optionC": "  Reserved for local use ",
            "optionD": "  Reserved for growing medicinal herbs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t\"Reserved Forests\" are forests Reserved for commercial exploitation and prohibited for grazing. At present, reserved forests and protected forests differ in one important way: Rights to all activities like hunting, grazing, etc. in reserved forests are banned unless specific orders are issued otherwise. ",
            "keyString": "812316s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In ________ forest, trees shed their leaves in a particular season.",
            "optionA": "  Evergreen ",
            "optionB": "  Mangrove ",
            "optionC": "  Deciduous ",
            "optionD": "  Thorny ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTemperate deciduous forests (or) temperate broad leaf forests are dominated by trees that loose their leaves each year in a particular season. Deciduous means \"falling off at maturity\" (or) \"tending to fall off'. Deciduous forests are located primarily in the regions of the world like eastern half of the United States,Canada, Europe, parts of Russia, China and Japan. Tropical moist deciduous forests are also found in India where the rain fall is around 100-200 cm.",
            "keyString": "813137s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following cities never experiences vertical rays of the sun during noon?",
            "optionA": "  Chennai ",
            "optionB": "  Mangalore ",
            "optionC": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionD": "  New Delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNew Delhi never experiences vertical rays of the sun during noon. Any place outside the tropics will never get vertical rays of the sun. ",
            "keyString": "813934s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Himalayan Range is very rich in species diversity. Which one among the following is the most appropriate reason -for this phenomenon?",
            "optionA": "  It has a high rainfall that supports luxuriant vegetative growth ",
            "optionB": "  It is a confluence of different bio-geographical zones ",
            "optionC": "  Exotic and invasive species have not been introduced in this region ",
            "optionD": "  It has less human interference ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Himalayan Range is very rich in species diversity because it is a confluence of different bio-geographical zones. ",
            "keyString": "814482s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Xerophytic vegetation is characteristic feature of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Chhotanagpur plateau ",
            "optionB": "  Khasi hills ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  Kuchchh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXerophytic vegetation is characteristic feature of Kuchchh. A xerophyte is a species of plant that has adaptations to survive in an environment with little liquid water, such as a desert or an ice- or snow-covered region in the Alps or the Arctic. ",
            "keyString": "815032s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Forest policy of govt. aims to bring what percentage of total area, under forest?",
            "optionA": "  33 ",
            "optionB": "  25 ",
            "optionC": "  22 ",
            "optionD": "  27 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia targets bringing 33\u00b0 of its geographical area under forest cover. As many as 15 states and union territories (UTs) have forest cover exceeding 33\u00b0 of their geographical area. ",
            "keyString": "901033s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of climate(s) prevail(s) in the long corridor (Leeward side) of the Western Ghats and the Nilgiri Hills?",
            "optionA": "  Tropical wet and dry climate ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical wet and dry with winter rain ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical semi-arid steppe ",
            "optionD": "  Subtropical monsoon rainforest ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTropical semi-arid steppe climate(s) prevail(s) in the long corridor (Leeward side) of the Western Ghats and the Nilgiri Hills. Regions with semi-arid climates represent the second driest climates in the world after deserts, known for their dry, arid climates. Semi-arid climates break down into two distinct classifications: hot and cold. Semi-arid climates are also known as steppe climates. ",
            "keyString": "901087s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Moist tropical evergreen forests are found in ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The Shillong plateau ",
            "optionB": "  The Siwaliks ",
            "optionC": "  The Deccan plateau ",
            "optionD": "  Southern India ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMoist tropical evergreen forests are found in The Shillong plateau. Tropical evergreen forests in our country are found mainly in the rainy tracts of the Sahyadris and the hill regions of the Shillong plateau. ",
            "keyString": "901241s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important commercial forests of India are ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Tropical evergreen ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical deciduous ",
            "optionC": "  Coniferous ",
            "optionD": "  Mangrove ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important commercial forests of India are Tropical deciduous. As per the economic resource pooling of India, the tropical Deciduous forests are the best ones in terms of export, import and revenue. ",
            "keyString": "901367s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amritsar and Shimla have the same latitude yet Shimla is cooler than Amritsar because it ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lies north of Amritsar ",
            "optionB": "  Comes under the influence of cold winds ",
            "optionC": "  Is at a higher elevation ",
            "optionD": "  Receives a lot of snow ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmritsar and Shimla have the same latitude yet Shimla is cooler than Amritsar because it Is at a higher elevation. Though both the cities lie on the same latitude, Shimla is situated on a much higher altitude. This is the cause of Shimla having lower temperature and much cooler than Amritsar. ",
            "keyString": "901478s41m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Delhi gets winter rainfall due to",
            "optionA": "  South west monsoon ",
            "optionB": "  North east monsoon ",
            "optionC": "  Conventional rain ",
            "optionD": "  Western distubances ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDelhi gets winter rainfall due to Western distubances. Western disturbances, specifically the ones in winter, bring moderate to heavy rain in low-lying areas and heavy snow to mountainous areas of the Indian Subcontinent. During the winters, the low pressure belt of temperate zone slides down over the Northern India. Due to which the feeble temperate cyclones originating over Mediterranean Sea move along western jet stream strikes North India. ",
            "keyString": "10440s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What percent of Indian terrain receive annual rainfall below 75 cm.",
            "optionA": "  0.35 ",
            "optionB": "  0.45 ",
            "optionC": "  0.4 ",
            "optionD": "  0.3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t0.35% of Indian terrain receive annual rainfall below 75 cm. The proportion of area which receives annual rainfall less than 75 cm. is one third. Major part of country included in this proportion are subtropical arid and subtropical semi arid regions of India. e.g. Gujarat, Rajasthan, parts of Punjab ",
            "keyString": "10474s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why does a farmer plough his fields in summer?",
            "optionA": "  To prevent alkalinity of soil ",
            "optionB": "  To prevent acidity of soil ",
            "optionC": "  To prevent the surface from becoming hard ",
            "optionD": "  To fertilize the soil ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFarmer plough his fields in summer to prevent the surface from becoming hard. Summer ploughing improves soil structure due to alternate drying and cooling. Tillage improves soil aeration which helps in multiplication of micro-organisms. ",
            "keyString": "10491s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which region in India receives substantial rain during the winter month of January ?",
            "optionA": "  Kerala coast ",
            "optionB": "  Central India ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Rajasthan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPunjab receives substantial rain during the winter month of January. It also receives rain from the retreating monsoons. In addition to this it also receives rain from the North East Monsoons in winter, but the total amount of rain received is comparatively less as these winds are less forceful and carry less water. ",
            "keyString": "10504s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "South-west winds are attracted to Indian subcontinent in rainy season by which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Low air pressure in north-western India ",
            "optionB": "  Effect of north-eastern commercial winds ",
            "optionC": "  By the formation of cyclone at equator ",
            "optionD": "   Effect of eastern winds ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDue to excessive heating in north-western India in summer season, a low pressure zone is created over north-western India. As air travels from high pressure area to low pressure area southwest monsoon winds are attracted towards this part from adjacent Indian ocean. ",
            "keyString": "10516s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which region gets first monsoon in summer?",
            "optionA": "  Himalayas ",
            "optionB": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  Gangetic Plain ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWestern Ghats gets first monsoon in summer. As the summer (wet) monsoons approach the West Coast of India, they rise up the western Ghats (mountains) and the air cools. ",
            "keyString": "52209s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The northeastern hills that block the South West Monsoon winds and cause heavy rains in Assam are",
            "optionA": "  Arakan Yoma and Pegu Yoma ",
            "optionB": "  Garo, Khasi and Jaintia hills ",
            "optionC": "  Barail and Patkai hills ",
            "optionD": "  Khasi and Pegu Yoma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe northeastern hills that block the South West Monsoon winds and cause heavy rains in Assam are Garo, Khasi and Jaintia hills. ",
            "keyString": "52245s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The average annual temperature of a meteorological station is 26\u00b0C, its average annual rainfall is 63 cm and the annual range of temperature is 9\u00b0C. The station in question is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Allahabad ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai ",
            "optionC": "  Cherapunji ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe average annual temperature of a meteorological station is 26\u00b0C, its average annual rainfall is 63 cm and the annual range of temperature is 9\u00b0C. The station in question is Chennai. ",
            "keyString": "52262s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The reason for Rajasthan being deficient in rainfall is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The monsoon fail to reach this area ",
            "optionB": "  It is too hot ",
            "optionC": "  There is no water available and thus the winds remain dry ",
            "optionD": "  The winds do not come across any barrier to cause necessary uplift to be cooled ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe reason for Rajasthan being deficient in rainfall is the winds do not come across any barrier to cause necessary uplift to be cooled. There are multiple reasons behind Rajasthan receiving scanty rainfall. Firstly the Arabian Sea Branch of South West Monsoon that causes rains in Western and South-Western India runs parallel to the Aravalli range and thus hardly causes any rainfall as the winds do not get interrupted. ",
            "keyString": "52277s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The extreme of temperature between summer and winter is quite low in southern part of peninsular India mainly because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The adjoining oceans moderate the temperature ",
            "optionB": "  The sky is generally cloudy ",
            "optionC": "  The sun's rays are almost vertical throughout the year ",
            "optionD": "  Strong winds flow throughout the year ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe extreme of temperature between summer and winter is quite low in southern part of peninsular India mainly because the adjoining oceans moderate the temperature. The southern parts of the country are distinctly warmer in March and April whereas in June, north India has higher temperatures. In March, the highest temperatures occur in the southern parts (40-45\u00b0C). ",
            "keyString": "52291s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The wet hill forest are found in the ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Aravallis ",
            "optionB": "  Mahadev Hills ",
            "optionC": "  Nilgiris ",
            "optionD": "  Satpura Hills ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe wet hill forest are found in the Nilgiris. These forests occur above 1,500 m height on the south Indian hills of Nilgiri, Annamalai and Palni and are locally known as sholas.",
            "keyString": "92394s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Norwesters are thunder storms which are prominent in ________.",
            "optionA": "  India and Bhutan ",
            "optionB": "  Bhutan and Nepal ",
            "optionC": "  India and Bangladesh ",
            "optionD": "  Bangladesh and Myanmar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorwesters are regional thunder storms that blow over India and Bangladesh. These thunder storms are very destructive speciallyin Bengal region and are also known \"KalBaisakhi\" . ",
            "keyString": "92427s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The driest part in India is in",
            "optionA": "  Jaisalmer (Western Rajasthan) ",
            "optionB": "  Bhatinda (Punjab) ",
            "optionC": "  Darbhanga (Bihar) ",
            "optionD": "  Gandhinagar (Gujarat) ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe driest part in India is in Jaisalmer (Western Rajasthan). Jaisalmer receives less than 12 km of rain because of its distance from Bay of Bengal, monsoon winds and its location in the sub - tropical high pressure belt. ",
            "keyString": "92444s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following areas of India is covered by tropical evergreen forest?",
            "optionA": "  Semi-arid areas of Gujarat ",
            "optionB": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionC": "  Western Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tropical evergreen forests are found in areas receiving more than 200 cm of rainfall. The tropical evergreen forests are found on the eastern and western slopes of the Western Ghats in states such as Tamil Nadu, Kerala, Karnataka, and Maharashtra. They are also found in Assam, Arunachal Pradesh, Nagaland, Tripura, Meghalaya, West Bengal and Andaman and Nicobar Islands. ",
            "keyString": "92459s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following region is covered by tropical evergreen forest?",
            "optionA": "  Eastern Ghat ",
            "optionB": "  Vindhyanchal ",
            "optionC": "  Aravalli ",
            "optionD": "  Western Ghat ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWestern Ghat is covered by tropical evergreen forest. In India, evergreen forests are found in the western slopes of the Western Ghats in States such as Kerala and Karnataka. They are also found in hills of Jaintia and Khasi. Some of the trees found in Indian Tropical Forests are rosewood, mahagony and ebony. Bamboos and reeds are also common. ",
            "keyString": "92472s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. The south-west monsoon causes heavy rainfall in the Shillong plateau.\n2. The north-east monsoon causes the rainfall over Orissa coast during winter.\nWhich of these statements is/are correct ?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe south-west monsoon causes heavy rainfall in the Shillong plateau. Guwahati, being in the rain shadow of the Meghalaya plateau, receives only 1,717 mm of rain. About 90 % of the rain is received during the southwest summer monsoon, and June is by far the rainiest month. Shillong plateau with its southern limit marked by a 1,200-m-high scarp overlooking the Bangladesh plain receives very heavy rains. ",
            "keyString": "128353s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following shows the correct sequence of places in descending order of the average summer rainfall ?",
            "optionA": "  Jaisalmer, Pune, Allahabad, Cherapunji ",
            "optionB": "  Cherapunji, Jaisalmer, Pune, Allahabad ",
            "optionC": "  Allahabad, Pune, Jaisalmer, Cherapunji ",
            "optionD": "  Cherapunji, Allahabad, Pune, Jaisalmer ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following that shows the correct sequence of places in descending order of the average summer rainfall are Cherapunji, Allahabad, Pune and Jaisalmer. ",
            "keyString": "128388s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following receives rainfall by north-eastern monsoon?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionB": "  Assam ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "   West Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTamil Nadu which lies on Coromandel coast receives rainfall during the winter season specially in months of October and November. This happens because it falls in the way retreating of north-east monsoonal winds. ",
            "keyString": "128403s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Heavy rainfall during the months of October and\nNovember is received by",
            "optionA": "  Gharo, Khasi and Jaintia hills ",
            "optionB": "  Chota Nagpur Plateau ",
            "optionC": "  Coromandel Coast ",
            "optionD": "  Malwa Plateau ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the months of October & November monsoon retreats from North India, meaning complete reversal of wind pattern. While movingas North-easterlies monsoon winds over Bay of Bengal they strike the Coromandal coast giving enormous rain to the region. ",
            "keyString": "128417s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. Tamil Nadu is the only area which receives about half of its rainfall from north-east monsoon winds.\n2. Kerala is the only state receiving very heavy rainfall from the south-west monsoon winds.\n3. In India, the south-west monsoon is stronger than the north-east monsoon.\nWhich of these are correct statements?",
            "optionA": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 ",
            "optionD": "  2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the three statements are correct. Tamil Nadu is the only area which receives about half of its rainfall from north-east monsoon winds. Kerala is the only state receiving very heavy rainfall from the south-west monsoon winds. In India, the south-west monsoon is stronger than the north-east monsoon. ",
            "keyString": "128430s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The mangrove forests are present in",
            "optionA": "  The Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionB": "  The Sunderbans ",
            "optionC": "  The Western Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  The Aravallis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe mangrove forests are present in The Sunderbans. The Sundarbans is a cluster of low-lying islands in the Bay of Bengal, spread across India and Bangladesh, famous for its unique mangrove forests. This active delta region is among the largest in the world, measuring about 40,000 sq km. ",
            "keyString": "157523s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "1. The Shivaliks have tropical moist deciduous flora.\n2. The Bundelkhand plateau has thorn and scrub forest type of vegetation.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth the given statements are correct. The Shivaliks have tropical moist deciduous flora. The Bundelkhand plateau has thorn and scrub forest type of vegetation. ",
            "keyString": "157557s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. In India, Red Panda is naturally found in the Western Himalayas only.\n2. In India, Slow Loris lives in the dense forests of the North East.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statement that is correct is that in India, Slow Loris lives in the dense forests of the North East. The Bengal slow loris (Nycticebus bengalensis) or northern slow loris is a strepsirrhine primate and a species of slow loris native to the Indian subcontinent and Indochina. ",
            "keyString": "157576s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of th following coasts of India is most affected by violent tropical cyclones?",
            "optionA": "  Malabar ",
            "optionB": "  Andhra Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Konkan ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs most of the cyclonic storms are formed in the Bay of Bengal which lies to the east of India. The eastern coast is severely affected by such storms. One of the parts of eastern coast is Coromandal or Cholamandalam or Andhra coasts.",
            "keyString": "193186s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following pairs is not correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Flood-prone area: North Bihar Plain ",
            "optionB": "  Drought-prone area: Kalahandi district of Orissa ",
            "optionC": "  Seismic zone: Himalayan region ",
            "optionD": "  Landslide zone: Chhotanaqpur plateau ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major landslide prone areas in India include the Western Ghats and Konkan Hills (Tamil Nadu, Kerala, Karnataka, Goa and Maharashtra), Eastern Ghats (Araku region in Andhra Pradesh), North-East Himalayas (Darjeeling and Sikkim) and North West Himalayas (Uttarakhand, Himachal Pradesh, Jammu and Kashmir). ",
            "keyString": "193218s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to Indian forests, consider the following pairs:\n1. Tropical Moist Deciduous Forests Sandalwood (Santalum album)\n2. Tropical Dry Deciduous Forests: (Shorea robusta)\n3. Tropical Thorn Forests: Shisham (Dalbeigia sissoo)\nWhich of the pairs given above is/are correctly matched?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  1 and 2 only ",
            "optionC": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pairs given above is/are correctly matched are Tropical Moist Deciduous Forests Sandalwood (Santalum album) and Tropical Dry Deciduous Forests: (Shorea robusta). ",
            "keyString": "193234s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Coastal Andhra Pradesh and Orissa often face natural disasters due to ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cyclones ",
            "optionB": "  Earthquakes ",
            "optionC": "  Landslides ",
            "optionD": "  Tornadoes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoastal Andhra Pradesh and Orissa often face natural disasters due to Cyclones. India is highly vulnerable to natural hazards especially earthquakes, floods, drought, cyclones and landslides. Four States (Andhra Pradesh, Odisha, Tamil Nadu and West Bengal) and one UT (Pondicherry) on the East Coast and One State (Gujarat) on the West Coast are more vulnerable to cyclone disasters. ",
            "keyString": "193252s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "India is particularly poor in reserves of",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Iron ore ",
            "optionC": "  Non-ferrous metals ",
            "optionD": "  Limestone ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia is particularly poor in reserves of Non-ferrous metals. Non-Ferrous Metals do not contain Iron, are not magnetic and are usually more resistant to corrosion than ferrous metals. ",
            "keyString": "193265s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state has become India's first carbon free state?",
            "optionA": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHimachal Pradesh has mandated all government departments to begin environment audit. Also involvment of people of Himachal Pradesh by bringing change in their lifestyle will boost this program. ",
            "keyString": "229046s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mangrove forests of Ganga delta are known as",
            "optionA": "  Monsoon forest ",
            "optionB": "  Sundarban ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical forest ",
            "optionD": "  Swamp forest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMangroves are submerged coastal forests located in tropical and subtropical coastal and deltaic marshy lands.These are intertidal zone forests with shrubs and short trees. The most distinctive tree of these forests is 'Sundari\" tree. ",
            "keyString": "229083s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which one of the following places is the monkey called Lion-tailed macaque naturally found?",
            "optionA": "  Shivaliks ",
            "optionB": "  Pachmarhi ",
            "optionC": "  Nallamalai hills ",
            "optionD": "  Nilgiris ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt Nilgiris, monkey called Lion-tailed macaque naturally found. Nilgiri Langur also known as Indian Hooded Leaf Monkey is another species of old world monkey, found in the Nilgiri Hills of the Western Ghats in South India. This primate also has glossy black fur as Lion Tailed Macaque but larger then in size with a long tail like gray langurs. ",
            "keyString": "229099s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a species of tropical moist deciduous forests?",
            "optionA": "  Mahagony ",
            "optionB": "  Sal ",
            "optionC": "  Shisham ",
            "optionD": "  Teak ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMahagony is not a species of tropical moist deciduous forests. Mahogany is a straight-grained, reddish-brown timber of three tropical hardwood species of the genus Swietenia, indigenous to the Americas and part of the pantropical chinaberry family, Meliaceae. ",
            "keyString": "229113s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ Oilfield of India has the largest quantity of recoverable reserves.",
            "optionA": "  Moran Oilfield ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai High (off shore) Oilfield ",
            "optionC": "  Ankaleshwar Oilfield ",
            "optionD": "  Naharkatiya Oilfield ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumbai High (off shore) Oilfield of India has the largest quantity of recoverable reserves. The Mumbai High Offshore Oil field is considered asa giant Oil field. An Oilfield to be categorised as a giant should have a minimum of 500 million barrels of recoverable crude oil. ",
            "keyString": "229126s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements is wrong regarding the \"Norwesters\" of Bengal?",
            "optionA": "  It is caused due to strong surface heating ",
            "optionB": "  It originates in the Chhotanagpur plateau region ",
            "optionC": "  It is a kind of thunderstorm ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the following statements are correct regarding the \"Norwesters\" of Bengal. It is caused due to strong surface heating, It originates in the Chhotanagpur plateau region and It is a kind of thunderstorm. ",
            "keyString": "263194s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The driest part of India is",
            "optionA": "  Darbhanga (Bihar) ",
            "optionB": "  Bhatinda (Punjab) ",
            "optionC": "  Gandhinagar (Gujarat) ",
            "optionD": "  Jaisalmer (Rajasthan) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:Jaisalmer is situated in the middle of the Thar Desert. Temperatures reach their peak in both summer and winter. Summer has a maximum temperature of 49\u00ba C and a minimum of 25\u00ba C. The maximum temperature in winter is 23\u00ba C and the minimum temperature is 5\u00ba C. The average rainfall is 210 mm. The maximum temperature was recorded at 50 \u00b0C. Hence it is called the driest place in India. ",
            "keyString": "263227s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the driest region in India?",
            "optionA": "  Telangana ",
            "optionB": "  Marwar ",
            "optionC": "   Vidarbha ",
            "optionD": "  Marathwada ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe western Rajasthan is the driest region of India which includes Marwar, as it receives less than 25 cm of rainfall annually. Hence, it becomes the part of \"Great Indian Desert\" i.e., Marusthali. It lies in high pressure subtropical zone and towards west of Indian subcontinent.",
            "keyString": "263243s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Riparian forest is found ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Along the banks of rivers and other wetland ",
            "optionB": "  The tarai region, on the foot hills of Himalayas ",
            "optionC": "  On the foot hills of Eastern slope of Western Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  On the foot hills of Eastern slope of Eastern Ghats ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRiparian forest is found Along the banks of rivers and other wetland. A riparian zone or riparian area is the interface between land and a river or stream. Riparian is also the proper nomenclature for one of the terrestrial biomes of the Earth. Plant habitats and communities along the river margins and banks are called riparian vegetation, characterized by hydrophilic plants. ",
            "keyString": "263256s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not true?",
            "optionA": "  The intensity of monsoons is determined by tropical depressions ",
            "optionB": "  Tamil Nadu receives rainfall from north-east monsoon ",
            "optionC": "  Andhra Pradesh is not much affected by retreating south-west monsoon ",
            "optionD": "  All are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll are correct. ",
            "keyString": "263269s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The retreating monsoon withdraws itself from",
            "optionA": "  The west coast to the east coast ",
            "optionB": "  North-East India to the west coast ",
            "optionC": "  The north to the south ",
            "optionD": "  North-West India to Bengal and then to Kerala ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe retreating monsoon withdraws itself from North-West India to Bengal and then to Kerala. When the retreating monsoon blows from the northeast across the Bay of Bengal, it picks up a significant amount of moisture, which is subsequently released after moving back onto the peninsula.",
            "keyString": "300271s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In May-June each year, the monsoon winds approach the southern tip of India from ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Northly direction ",
            "optionB": "  North-easterly direction ",
            "optionC": "  North-westerly direction ",
            "optionD": "  South-westerly direction ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn May-June each year, the monsoon winds approach the southern tip of India from South-westerly direction because winds blow from high to low pressure, warm moisture-laden air moves south-westerly direction from the sea over to India in the north and North East and is deflected by the Coriolis force as the Earth spins. It is this moist air current which is popularly known as the south-west monsoon. ",
            "keyString": "300324s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The premonsoon mango showers occur predominantly in",
            "optionA": "  West Bengal and Assam ",
            "optionB": "  Deccan Plateau ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat and Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Kerala and Karnataka ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe premonsoon mango showers occur predominantly in West Bengal and Assam. The pre monsoon showers are a consequence of these thunder-storms. These showers not only cause the early ripening of the mangoes but also prevents the amateur mango buds from falling down by controlling wind. ",
            "keyString": "300348s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are the main reasons for the origin of the south-west monsoon in India?\nI. Development of a low pressure in north-west India\nII. Deflection of trade winds\nIII. Arrival of cyclonic stream from the Pacific Ocean\nIV. Heating of the Arabian Sea and the Bay of Bengal",
            "optionA": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionB": "  I and II ",
            "optionC": "  II and III ",
            "optionD": "  III and IV ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main reasons for the origin of the south-west monsoon in India are Development of a low pressure in north-west India and Deflection of trade winds. These winds originate in the Southern Hemisphere, cross the Equator (trade winds) and gets deflected to the right by the Coriolis force in the Northern Hemisphere. ",
            "keyString": "300366s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian monsoon is marked by seasonal shift caused by ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Differential heating of land and sea ",
            "optionB": "  Cold winds of Central Asia ",
            "optionC": "  Great uniformity of temperature ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian monsoon is marked by seasonal shift caused by differential heating of land and sea. The climate of India depends greatly on monsoon winds. The monsoons usually happen due to the differential heating of land and water. Normally, there is high pressure in the tropical eastern-south Pacific Ocean and low pressure in the tropical eastern Indian Ocean. ",
            "keyString": "300385s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following wind is blowing from the Mediterranean sea to the North Western parts of India?",
            "optionA": "  Western disturbances ",
            "optionB": "  Norwesters ",
            "optionC": "   Loo ",
            "optionD": "  Mango showers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFeeble temperate cyclone (Western disturbance) blows from the Mediterranean Sea to the north western part of India. This system bring rain to Indian states like Haryana, Punjab & western U.P. etc. which is highlybeneficial for the reaping of wheat crop (Rabi crop). It generally precipitates in the months of February and March. ",
            "keyString": "342361s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The flash flood is related with which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Incessant storm ",
            "optionB": "  Cyclonic storm ",
            "optionC": "  Tsunami ",
            "optionD": "  Tornado ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTorrential downpours associated with cyclonic storm brings heavy rainfall in a particular short span of time and causes flood like situation often termes flash food. ",
            "keyString": "342397s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following types of forest covers the maximum area in India?",
            "optionA": "  Tropical rain forest ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical moist deciduous forest ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical dry deciduous forest ",
            "optionD": "  Tropical dry evergreen forest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTropical moist deciduous forest covers the maximum area in India. Tropical dry deciduous forests run from the Himalayan foot hills to Kanyakumari and comprise important trees like bijasal, teak, tendu, amaltas, khair, palas, rosewood and axlewood. ",
            "keyString": "342413s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Himalayan forests include",
            "optionA": "  European Oak Forests ",
            "optionB": "  Coniferous Forests ",
            "optionC": "  Alpine Vegetation ",
            "optionD": "  All the three ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Himalayan forests include European Oak Forests, Coniferous Forests and Alpine Vegetation. ",
            "keyString": "342427s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"Central India Teak\" is an Example of",
            "optionA": "  Tropical Evergreen Forest ",
            "optionB": "  Moist Deciduous Forest ",
            "optionC": "  Dry Deciduous Forest ",
            "optionD": "  Montane Forest ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"Central India Teak\" is an Example of Moist Deciduous Forest. Moist deciduous forests are found throughout India except in the western and the north-western regions. The trees have broad trunks, are tall and have branching trunks and roots to hold them firmly to the ground. Some of the taller trees shed their leaves in the dry season. There is a layer of shorter trees and evergreen shrubs in the undergrowth. These forests are dominated by sal and teak, along with mango, bamboo, and rosewood. ",
            "keyString": "342441s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of India's rainfall is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cyclonic ",
            "optionB": "  Convectional ",
            "optionC": "  Elusive ",
            "optionD": "  Orographic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of India's rainfall is convectional. The convectional rainfall is prevalent in equatorial regions. In these, the warm air rises up and expands then, reaches at a cooler layer and saturates, then condenses mainly in the form of cumulus or cumulonimbus clouds. In the equatorial regions, the precipitation due to convectional rainfall occurs in the afternoon. ",
            "keyString": "382957s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rainfall in India is not associated with ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Orography ",
            "optionB": "  Convection ",
            "optionC": "  Cyclones ",
            "optionD": "  Anticyclones ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRainfall in India is not associated with anticyclones. An 'anticyclone' is opposite to a cyclone, in which winds move into a low-pressure area. In an anticyclone, winds move out from a high-pressure area with wind direction clockwise in the northern hemisphere, anti-clockwise in the southern hemisphere. ",
            "keyString": "383046s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of India receives rainfall from both the South-West and North-West monsoons?",
            "optionA": "  Tamilnadu ",
            "optionB": "  Odisha ",
            "optionC": "  Lakshadweep Islands ",
            "optionD": "  Andaman and Nicobar Islands ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAndaman and Nicobar Islands receives rainfall from both the South-West and North-West monsoons. Southwest monsoon has covered the Nicobar Islands and the entire south Andaman Sea. ",
            "keyString": "383094s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following characteristics are associated with the dry monsoon forest of India?\n1. Annual rainfall is below 50 cm\n2. The trees are short rooted\n3. Thorny shrubs and grassland\n4. Mango, Mahua, Sisam and Keeker are the prominent trees.",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 4 ",
            "optionC": "  3 and 4 ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following characteristics that are associated with the dry monsoon forest of India are mango, mahua, sisam and keeker are the prominent trees and thorny shrubs and grassland. Monsoon forest, also called dry forest or tropical deciduous forest, open woodland in tropical areas that have a long dry season followed by a season of heavy rainfall. ",
            "keyString": "383118s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Paddy fields of India are located in the areas of annual rainfall",
            "optionA": "  120 cm ",
            "optionB": "  140 cm ",
            "optionC": "  100 cm ",
            "optionD": "  80 cm ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Paddy fields of India are located in the areas of annual rainfall 100cm. Paddy has become an important crop of Punjab and Haryana. It requires high humidity with an annual rainfall above 100 cm. ",
            "keyString": "383147s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are Rain forests found?",
            "optionA": "  Central India ",
            "optionB": "  Eastern Ghats ",
            "optionC": "  North-Eastern Himalayas and Western Ghats ",
            "optionD": "  North-Western Himalayas and Eastern Ghats ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth eastern Himalayas and western Ghats are the regions in India having rainfall greater than 200 cm. Due to high temperature and high precipitation Rainforests exist in these places.",
            "keyString": "437882s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements:\n1. In the wet temperate forests at above 1500 m on the Nilgiris and Anaimalais, the Magnolias and Rhododendrons are commonly found.\n2. Tropical dry evergreen forests are mostly found in Andhra Pradesh, Chhattisgarh and Orissa.\nWhich of the statements given above is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the wet temperate forests at above 1500 m on the Nilgiris and Anaimalais, the Magnolias and Rhododendrons are commonly found. ",
            "keyString": "437984s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Winter rains in North and North-West India are generally associated with the phenomenon of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Retreating monsoon ",
            "optionB": "  Temperate cyclones ",
            "optionC": "  Local thunderstorms ",
            "optionD": "  Shift in jet stream movement ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWinter rains in North and North-West India are generally associated with the phenomenon of Temperate cyclones. In the winter season temperature cyclon occured in Arabean sea. This phenomenon led a rain in the North-West India. ",
            "keyString": "438047s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The nature of the winter rainfall in north western India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Convectional ",
            "optionB": "  Orographic ",
            "optionC": "  Monsoonal ",
            "optionD": "  Cyclonic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nature of the winter rainfall in north western India is cyclonic. Frontal (or Cyclonic) Rain is caused by cyclonic activity and it occurs along the fronts of the cyclone. It is formed when two masses of air of different temperature, humidity and density meets.",
            "keyString": "438092s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following area of Indian subcontinent becomes the area of low pressure in summer?",
            "optionA": "  Rann of Kutch ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  North Western India ",
            "optionD": "  Meghalaya ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth Western India area of Indian subcontinent becomes the area of low pressure in summer. In summer season due to highly heated earth surface, air rises and north western India in particular becomes an area of low pressure of around 970mb. ",
            "keyString": "438133s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following cities of India the diurnal range of temperature is maximum?",
            "optionA": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Mumbai ",
            "optionC": "  Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  Kolkata ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn New Delhi the diurnal range of temperature is maximum. The mean annual temperature in New Delhi, India is fairly hot at 25.1\u00b0 Celsius (77.2\u00b0 Fahrenheit). There is a variation of mean monthly temperatures of 19.1\u00b0C (34.4\u00b0F) which is a slightly low range. The variation/ range of diurnal average temperatures is 12.3\u00b0C (22.1\u00b0F). ",
            "keyString": "478143s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chennai receives less rainfall by South-West Monsoon than other places, because",
            "optionA": "  Monsoon travels parallel to Coromandel Coast ",
            "optionB": "  Chennai is very hot place and do not allow humidity\nto evaporate ",
            "optionC": "  These winds are off shore monsoon winds ",
            "optionD": "  Above all ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChennai lies on Coromandal coast which liles parallel to south-west monsoon winds which blow off shore here. Also it is highly hot and humid region due to its proximity to the equator and sea.",
            "keyString": "478176s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cherapunji receives more rainfall than Shillong because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The former is nearer to the sea ",
            "optionB": "  The air of different densities and temperature tends to converge towards Cherapunji from different direction during the rainy season ",
            "optionC": "  Cherapunji is located on the windward side ",
            "optionD": "  Convective precipitation brings more rain at Cherapunji ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCherapunji receives more rainfall than Shillong because the air of different densities and temperature tends to converge towards Cherapunji from different direction during the rainy season. Cherrapunji receives both the southwest and northeast monsoonal winds, giving it a single monsoon season. It lies on the windward side of the Khasi Hills, so the resulting orographic lift enhances precipitation. ",
            "keyString": "478193s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Taking into account the amount of rainfall occurring from June to September, which one of the following is the correct order of cities in terms of rainfall?",
            "optionA": "  Kolkata > Ahmedabad > Allahabad ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata > Allahabad > Ahmedabad ",
            "optionC": "  Allahabad > Kolkata > Ahmedabad ",
            "optionD": "  Ahmedabad > Kolkata > Allahabad ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTaking into account the amount of rainfall occurring from June to September, the following is the correct order of cities in terms of rainfall Kolkata, Allahabad and then Ahmedabad. ",
            "keyString": "478205s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following places, which one receives comparatively lowest average monsoon rainfall from June to September?",
            "optionA": "  Eastern Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Southern West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Punjab ",
            "optionD": "  Western Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong the following places, Western Uttar Pradesh receives comparatively lowest average monsoon rainfall from June to September. Uttar Pradesh received lowest rainfall in prime monsoon. ",
            "keyString": "478219s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is characterized by excessive dampness with a thick growth forest and a variety of wild life?",
            "optionA": "  Bhabar ",
            "optionB": "  Bhangar ",
            "optionC": "  Tarai ",
            "optionD": "  Khadar ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTarai is characterized by excessive dampness with a thick growth forest and a variety of wild life. It is a marshy tract and zone of excessive dampness with a thick growth of forests and a variety of wildlife.",
            "keyString": "521825s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indus Valley Civilization was based on the racial stocks of",
            "optionA": "  Mediterraneans ",
            "optionB": "  Nordics ",
            "optionC": "  Negritos ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilization was based on the racial stocks of Mediterraneans. It is considered that they were the people who, in collaboration with the Mediterranean race, had developed the Indus Valley Civilization. ",
            "keyString": "521858s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which city has the longest day in the month of June?",
            "optionA": "  Delhi ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Chennai ",
            "optionD": "  Bangalore ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKolkata has the longest day in the month of June. Over the course of June in Kolkata, the length of the day is essentially constant. The shortest day of the month is June 1, with 13 hours, 25 minutes of daylight and the longest day is June 21, with 13 hours, 31 minutes of daylight. ",
            "keyString": "521872s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In India the State with the largest area under very dense forests is",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Madhya Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Maharashtra ",
            "optionD": "  Orissa ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn India the State with the largest area under very dense forests is Arunachal Pradesh. Arunachal Pradesh in terms of percentage of forest cover with respect to total geographical area. ",
            "keyString": "521908s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following places ranks second among the coldest places in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Dras (Jammu and Kashmir) ",
            "optionB": "  Kullu (Himachal Pradesh) ",
            "optionC": "  Manali (Himachal Pradesh) ",
            "optionD": "  Itanagar (Arunachal Pradesh) ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDras (Jammu and Kashmir) ranks second among the coldest places in the world. A lonely town in the infamous Kargil district of Jammu and Kashmir, Dras is popularly known as 'the gateway to Ladakh'. It is known to be the coldest place in India and often touted as second to the coldest place inhabited on Earth. ",
            "keyString": "521931s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Littoral forests occur",
            "optionA": "  On hills ",
            "optionB": "  Along the sea coasts and tidal creeks ",
            "optionC": "  Where the rainfall is heavy ",
            "optionD": "  At elevated places ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLittoral forests occur Along the sea coasts and tidal creeks. Littoral forests and Swamp forests are also called the wetland forests. India has rich variety of these type of forest. They are mainly found in reservoirs of Deccan Plateau, saline coast of Gujarat, Rajasthan and Gulf of Kutch, Eastern Coast Deltas, lakes and Rivers of Kashmir and Ladakh, Swamps in North East India. ",
            "keyString": "558137s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The coastal Andhra Pradesh and Orissa have to face which of the following natural calamity?",
            "optionA": "  Cyclone ",
            "optionB": "  Earthquake ",
            "optionC": "  Landslide ",
            "optionD": "  Tornado ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe low pressure areas over Bay of Bengal travels as depressions towards coastal India. These depressions attract air and swirling air takes the form of cyclone which hits the coastal areas of Andhra and Orissa. ",
            "keyString": "558167s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which place will you find maximum sunlight in December?",
            "optionA": "  Pune ",
            "optionB": "  Leh ",
            "optionC": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionD": "  Kanyakumari ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt Kanyakumari you will find maximum sunlight in December. Kanyakumari is nearest to the Tropic of Capricorn, and the sun's rays fall vertically here during December. ",
            "keyString": "558181s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Open stunted forests with bushes and having long roots and sharp thorns or spines are commonly found in",
            "optionA": "  Eastern Odisha ",
            "optionB": "  North-Eastern Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionC": "  Shiwaliks and Terai regions ",
            "optionD": "  Western Andhra Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOpen stunted forests with bushes and having long roots and sharp thorns or spines are commonly found in Western Andhra Pradesh. Open stunted forests with bushes and small trees having long roots and sharp thorns or spines are commonly found in the area where the rainfall is less than 80 cm. Such areas are found in Rajasthan, Gujarat, Haryana and western Andhra Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "558193s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Forest of Sundarban is called as",
            "optionA": "  Thorn forest ",
            "optionB": "   Mangrove forest ",
            "optionC": "  Deciduous forest ",
            "optionD": "  Tundra ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSundarban is the coastal area in easter part of India near West Bengal having saline/brackish water where shrub or small trees grow. This group of trees and shrubs is known as mangrove forest. ",
            "keyString": "558205s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following receive, heavy rainfall in the month of October and November?",
            "optionA": "  Hills of Garo, Khasi and Jaintia ",
            "optionB": "   Plateau of Chota Nagpur ",
            "optionC": "  Coromandel Coast ",
            "optionD": "  Malwa Plateau ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the months of October and November the south west monsoon traces its path backward and is known as retreat of monsoon. It hits the Coromandel coast and brings a considerable amount of rainfall. This is also known as north-east monsoon. ",
            "keyString": "596726s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For short-term climatic predictions, which one of the following events, detected in the last decade, is associated with occasional weak monsoon rains in the Indian subcontinent?",
            "optionA": "  La Nina ",
            "optionB": "  Movement of jet streams ",
            "optionC": "  El Nino and southern oscillations ",
            "optionD": "  Green-house effect on global level ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor short-term climatic predictions, El Nino and southern oscillations, detected in the last decade, is associated with occasional weak monsoon rains in the Indian subcontinent. El Nino and the Southern Oscillation, also known as ENSO is a periodic fluctuation in sea surface temperature (El Nino) and the air pressure of the overlying atmosphere (Southern Oscillation) across the equatorial Pacific Ocean.",
            "keyString": "596761s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following state receives rainfall due to western disturbances?",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  West Bengal ",
            "optionC": "  Kerala ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPunjab receives rainfall due to western disturbances. Western disturbances are extra tropical storms that originate over Mediterranean and flows toward east. InIndia western disturbances bring winter rainfall in states like Punjab, Haryanana and western Uttar Pradesh. ",
            "keyString": "596778s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the monsoon season rainfall decreases from the Ganga delta to the Punjab plains. It is because ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Monsoon current moves westward along the Ganga plain and becomes drier ",
            "optionB": "  Western regions are warmer than the eastern region ",
            "optionC": "  Hills do not form barriers for winds ",
            "optionD": "  The area is far away from the sea ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the monsoon season rainfall decreases from the Ganga delta to the Punjab plains. It is because monsoon current moves westward along the Ganga plain and becomes drier. ",
            "keyString": "596792s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arrange the following cities in decreasing order of the rainfall they receive from the south-west monsoons in summer months:\n1. Allahabad\n2. Kolkata\n3. Delhi\n4. Patna",
            "optionA": "  2, 4, 1, 3 ",
            "optionB": "  3, 1, 4, 2 ",
            "optionC": "  1, 4, 3, 2 ",
            "optionD": "  2, 4, 3, 1 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following cities in decreasing order of the rainfall they receive from the south-west monsoons in summer months are Kolkata, Patna, Delhi and Allahabad. ",
            "keyString": "596804s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rainfall from the south-west monsoon reaches ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lahauland Spiti ",
            "optionB": "  Ladakh ",
            "optionC": "  Tamil Nadu ",
            "optionD": "  Delta region of Mahanadi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRainfall from the south-west monsoon reaches Delta region of Mahanadi. Mahanadi River Delta in India is a basin of deposit that drains a large land mass of the Indian subcontinent into the Bay of Bengal. The alluvial valley is wide and relatively flat with a meandering river channel that changes its course. ",
            "keyString": "636022s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following regions of India, which one receives comparatively least amount of annual rainfall?",
            "optionA": "  An 80 km wide coastal belt from Nellore to Point Calimere ",
            "optionB": "  The middle and lower Asom valley ",
            "optionC": "  North-eastern Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  The coastal plains of Gujarat south of Narmada ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth-eastern Rajasthan receives comparatively least amount of annual rainfall. The eastern regions of the Rajasthan receives the total 100 cm annual rainfall. ",
            "keyString": "636055s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The winter rain in Chennai is caused by",
            "optionA": "  South-West Monsoons ",
            "optionB": "  North-East Monsoons ",
            "optionC": "  Intense Land and Sea Breezes ",
            "optionD": "  Cyclonic winds in the Bay of Bengal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe winter rain in Chennai is caused by North-East Monsoons. Tamil Nadu receives winter rainfall because of the retreating monsoon and the North-east Monsoon winds which pass over the Bay of Bengal, they get moisture and when they reach the Tamil Nadu coasts they cause rainfall there. ",
            "keyString": "636071s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The place in India receiving the lowest rainfall is",
            "optionA": "  Leh ",
            "optionB": "  Jaisalmer ",
            "optionC": "  Bikaner ",
            "optionD": "  Jodhpur ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe place in India receiving the lowest rainfall is Leh. The average annual precipitation in these regions is less than 50 cms. The cities like Jaisalmer in Rajasthan and Leh in Ladakh receives the least rainfall. ",
            "keyString": "636084s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nagpur gets scanty rainfall because it is located with reference to Sahyadri Mountains, towards ________.",
            "optionA": "  Windward Side ",
            "optionB": "  Seaward Side ",
            "optionC": "  Onshore Side ",
            "optionD": "  Leeward Side ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNagpur lies in interior Maharashtra towards the leeward side of Sahyadri Mountains. Most of the precipitation occurs to the west of Sahyadris. As winds pass over these mountains they become dry after shedding most of their moisture while rising against their high elevated peaks.",
            "keyString": "636097s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The tropical cyclones of the Bay of Bengal are usually called",
            "optionA": "  Typhoons ",
            "optionB": "  Hurricanes ",
            "optionC": "  Depressions ",
            "optionD": "  Tornadoes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tropical cyclones of the Bay of Bengal are usually called Hurricanes. The Bay of Bengal is one of the major centres of the world for breeding of tropical storms. These storms are known as cyclones over the Indian Ocean and south-western Pacific, as typhoons over the north-western Pacific, and as hurricanes over the Atlantic. ",
            "keyString": "679554s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is recognised as a season by the meteorological department of India ?",
            "optionA": "  Cold weather ",
            "optionB": "  Hot weather ",
            "optionC": "  Retreating monsoon ",
            "optionD": "  North-eastern monsoon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNorth-eastern monsoon is recognised as a season by the meteorological department of India. North East monsoon is the weak rain bearing seasonal winds that flow when the South West monsoon retreats from the Indian mainland. They pick-up the moisture mainly from Bay of Bengal and gives rain to many places in India during the months of October and November. ",
            "keyString": "679588s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A tropical deciduous plant special to the Deccan plateau is ________.",
            "optionA": "   Teak ",
            "optionB": "  Shisam ",
            "optionC": "  Sandalwood ",
            "optionD": "  Sal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSandalwood, a tropical decidous tree which lies in region of rainfall between 100 cm to 200 cm. It is a class of woods from trees in the genus santalum. Unlike many other aromatic woods these woods are heavy yellow and fine-grained. The deccan area lies in the region receiving between 100cm to 200cm rainfall.",
            "keyString": "679605s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following factors does not have influence on the Indian climate?",
            "optionA": "  Presence of Indian Ocean ",
            "optionB": "  Nearness to equator ",
            "optionC": "  Monsoons ",
            "optionD": "  Ocean currents ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOcean currents does not have influence on the Indian climate. Indian ocean is half an ocean, hence the behavior of the North Indian Ocean Currents is different from that of Atlantic Ocean Currents or the Pacific Ocean Currents. Also, monsoon winds in Northern Indian ocean are peculiar to the region, which directly influence the ocean surface water movement [North Indian Ocean Currents]. ",
            "keyString": "679619s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important commercial forests of India are",
            "optionA": "  Tropical evergreen ",
            "optionB": "  Mangrove ",
            "optionC": "  Tropical deciduous ",
            "optionD": "  Coniferous ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTropical decidious forests are the most commercially important tropical forest type found in India. A deciduous forest is a biome dominated by deciduous trees which lose their leaves seasonally. The Earth has temperate deciduous forests, and tropical and subtropical deciduous forests, also known as dry forests.",
            "keyString": "679632s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When did India adopt the International Tsunami Warning System",
            "optionA": "  2004 ",
            "optionB": "  2005 ",
            "optionC": "  2006 ",
            "optionD": "  2007 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndia adopt the International Tsunami Warning System in 2006. India agreed to \"Ocean Tsunami Warning System\" in a United Nations Conference held in January 2005 in Kobe, Japan. As an initiation towards an International Early Warning Programme after the disastrous tsunami of 2004 due to Indian Oceean earthquake. ",
            "keyString": "715720s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What do you mean by 'reserved forest' ?",
            "optionA": "  Reserved for local use ",
            "optionB": "  Reserved for commercial exploitation ",
            "optionC": "  Reserved for hunting ",
            "optionD": "  Reserved for growing medicinal herbs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t'Reserved forest' means Reserved for commercial exploitation. A reserved forest is a specific term for designating forests and other natural areas, which enjoy judicial and / or constitutional protection under the legal systems of many countries. ",
            "keyString": "715754s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the following states, in which one is the percentage of forest area to total geographical area the highest?",
            "optionA": "  Arunachal Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Himachal Pradesh ",
            "optionC": "  Sikkim ",
            "optionD": "  Uttarakhand ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArunachal Pradesh has the largest forest cover of 66,964 square km. ",
            "keyString": "715770s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the floods in the lowlands of north India, the Bihar plateau and Orissa are associated with ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Easterly depression ",
            "optionB": "  Orographic rainfall ",
            "optionC": "  South-West Monsoon ",
            "optionD": "  Thunderstorm ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the floods in the lowlands of north India, the Bihar plateau and Orissa are associated with Orographic rainfall. ",
            "keyString": "715784s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The climate of India is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Tropical climate ",
            "optionB": "  Sub-tropical climate ",
            "optionC": "  Savanna type of climate ",
            "optionD": "  Subtropical monsoon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe climate of India is Subtropical monsoon. Most of North-east India and much of North India are subject to a humid subtropical climate. Though they experience hot summers, temperatures during the coldest months may fall as low as 0\u00b0 C (32\u00b0 F). India is blessed with its location in the tropical region, therefore most of the rain is brought by the monsoon winds. ",
            "keyString": "715796s42m24h12d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}